Jason Arday was once the darling of
academia. Now he's resigned amid
scandal. A string of allegations
regarding plagiarism and tall tales
raised questions about himself,
Cambridge University, and higher
learning in general.
>> very inspiring and you
>> Arday became the youngest black
professor in Cambridge's history in
2023. A stunning achievement for someone
who said he was mute until 11, has
struggled with his autism, and left
school with two GCSEs.
>> I went to university at 20, but I had
the reading age of a 9-year-old. You
know, so you you you're trying to really
kind of
>> Really? I mean, is that possible?
>> Yeah, it is. Muhammad Ali spoke about
this idea of will versus skill.
Now, I don't have any
skill.
Um, but what I do have is an indomitable
will.
>> Concerns about Arday's credentials as a
professor of sociology of education have
swirled around Cambridge's spires for
years, but they came back to the fore
recently.
Writing on Substack, a self-described
race realist Nathan Cofnas wrote, "I was
recently contacted by a faculty member
at Cambridge who alleges that Arday is a
plagiarist and fabulist." He added, "I
ran Arday's 2015 PhD dissertation
through the plagiarism detection program
CopyLeaks. It found substantial overlap
with previously published work."
That dissertation was submitted to
Liverpool John Moores University. They
said a confidential procedure had been
conducted and that Arday's PhD still
stood. But two of his articles in
journals have been corrected in recent
years following further claims of
plagiarism, with Arday admitting to
referencing errors. Cambridge University
had begun an investigation as had his
college, Jesus. But then Arday resigned,
criticizing an unrelenting level of
scrutiny and attacks. Arday said that
while criticism is inevitable, "What I
have experienced has gone far beyond
scholarly disagreement. The relentless
accusations, speculation, and public
commentary have taken a profound toll on
me and on those I love. He said the
resignation should not be mistaken for
an acceptance of the narratives that
have surrounded me.
The allegation is that conservative
figures are taking down black academics
in their war on diversity.
Kofnas, who wrote that original Substack
about Arday, has himself been criticized
for his views on race and academia,
which have been described as deeply
offensive.
>> If your concern is about a very
important issue of plagiarism, are you
not concerned that those figures on the
right are actually using this to not
address something like that? They're
using it to attack diversity, to attack
sociology, to attack universities
themselves.
>> Well, uh that's possibly true, but
what's the best defense against that?
The best defense against that is for me
is to maintain academic standards, and
sociology does have
academic standards, and they they need
need to be maintained.
>> But another history professor at
Cambridge was found to have plagiarized
and remained in post just a few years
ago. Why was that not front-page news?
And is there a wider concern here about
plagiarism at a time when there is a
financial crisis at universities?
>> So they have to publish articles in the
best journals to almost survive these
calls of redundancies. Does that mean
there's a lot more more plagiarism?
Well, I'm sure there is pressure on some
academics to look at other people's
work.
>> Plagiarism is generally taken the least
seriously. A lot of charges have been
raised. They've, you know, been
confirmed, and many people remain in
their position.
>> Why is plagiarism not taken that
seriously?
>> I don't have a good answer for that,
honestly. I, you know, part of it is
there's the ability to deny it and say,
"Oh, this was just a little bit of
sloppiness."
>> But there were wider concerns with
Professor Arday. Talking to the
Guardian, he said a pig's head was once
sent to his parents' address, and that
police looked into the matter. But the
Met said no investigation had taken
place. And his Cambridge faculty page
said he had visiting professorships at
Glasgow and Ohio State Universities.
Both institutions have now said they
have no records of Arday holding such
positions.
>> Honestly, I would say this it taints the
repu- reputation of all academics and
and folks in these embattled humanities
fields.
>> But is there a concern there that this
is
that he's letting
figures down? Or is it that other
figures, black ethnic minority,
are looking at this and saying the
minute you put your head above the
parapet, you are hounded and hounded?
>> There's a bit of both in that, but he
was put up as a poster boy by Cambridge
in his biography and by the people who
appointed him there. Now, I'm going back
again to the
>> So, Cambridge has more to answer than
him.
>> Cambridge has Cambridge has something to
answer for this, yeah.
>> Arday has denied he is a liar and
fabulist and spoken about the scrutiny
he has faced and the pressure of his
role.
>> This might sound like a crazy thing to
say, but I I don't really like
research. I find it difficult. It's
Being an academic is really, really
difficult.
>> Just like with any thesis, there are
multiple chapters. Arday has questions
to answer, but there is also the concern
about his apparent hounding out at a
time when there are so few senior black
academics at universities. And there are
still plenty of questions for Cambridge
and whether the university did enough
not just to support Arday, but whether
they should have put him in this
position in the first place.
>> Gareth Modley reporting. Well, I've been
speaking to the academic and activist
Professor Gus John and Ian Pace, who's
Professor of Music, Culture and Society
at City and St. George's University in
London. I started by asking Gus John
whether he thought Mr. Arday had lost
his job because he was hounded out or
because of his own dishonesty.
>> Whatever his dishonesty may have been,
there's no question that people alighted
on his infractions or
issues to do with his qualifications and
and achievements
um
with a hostility which I think is
is is really due principally to people's
concerns about the the the abilities of
of black people.
>> I mean, he was accused of plagiarism.
You know, he is accused of, you know,
lying about some of his other
achievements. I mean, that is a fact, is
it not?
>> You are you are right. There are things
which, according to what I've read,
simply do not add up and require some
explanations.
>> Mhm.
>> Um now,
why these were not picked up earlier in
his career, I mean, after all, he'd been
to Ravensbourne, he's been to Durham,
he'd been to Glasgow before getting to
Cambridge,
I'm not quite sure.
But, it seems to me that that um along
the way, there were many people who
could have intervened
whether to correct what he was doing or
to say to him, he needed to be more
transparent about what he's saying his
achievements are. I don't know. But, it
seems to me that that there were
failings all along the way as far as he
was concerned.
>> Let's turn to you, Professor Ian Pace. I
mean,
is it fair to say that
Professor Jason Arday would not have
been hounded in the way that he was if
he had been white?
>> No, I don't accept that. I mean, if you
look at this This has been really quite
an incredible story and the amount of
things that have come out.
Uh
uh it just almost beggars belief at
times.
If I look first just at his work, cuz I
first became aware of this uh autumn of
last year when journalist Jack Grove uh
uh
approached me and approached a few other
academics. Uh he knew that I'd published
articles about plagiarism and so on. And
she said, "This is one of the biggest
cases he's ever seen in terms of the
sheer quantity." Based on what? Based on
examining his work in detail and finding
large passages which were lifted
verbatim or verbatim or near verbatim
from other scholars' work. If someone
was getting a doctoral degree in part by
passing someone else's work
>> Okay. But that is a But that's not the
first time that would have happened. I I
give you the case of Professor William
O'Reilly, a historian at Cambridge
University, found guilty of doing
exactly what you just described in 2023,
and guess what? Still teaching at
Cambridge as a professor.
>> I haven't investigated that case in
detail, so I would have to do that to
sort of ascertain the extent of the
plagiarism there. But I will say that
from my own investigation, you know, and
I've been I've been checking some of
Ardy's work myself, and I've read
through quite a lot of it. I'd say this
plagiarism is a consistent factor across
a whole range of it, not just the PhD
thesis. A fraction of that, if we saw
this in this in an undergraduate paper,
uh we would be have we reading the riot
act to them. I've been on many panels
where we've been doing that with
students and accused of plagiarism.
>> Can I Can I ask you both a question? I
mean, and and you referred to this, uh
Professor John, that that there was such
a long line of universities that should
have looked into his in into his record
and into his work more accurately, and
they didn't. So, is the university
system here at fault? They're just not
doing their job.
First, you.
>> Well, I I would I would say I would say
yes, because you see, I said earlier
that neurodiversity is a factor in this,
and it was a factor. I'm not quite sure
the extent to which adjustments,
reasonable adjustments, were made to
support him on his
in his academic career. I'm surprised
that some of the stuff that's emerging
now was not picked up by John Liverpool
John Moores 10 years ago or whatever it
is. Um And And when I say that he's been
and
along the way, what I'm actually saying
is that supervisors,
people who had the the job, never mind
the capacity,
to comment upon his work and give him
some developmental assistance on the
basis of their assessments, didn't do
so.
>> Yeah, but there are many people but
there are but but Professor, there are
many people who will say
the reason why they didn't do so is
because they were too woke. They didn't
want to ask the awkward questions.
>> That may be true in some some instances,
but in other instances, I believe that
it is because people were not diligent
enough
about ensuring that he was given the
kind of support and assistance that he
needed.
>> Professor Pace, perhaps finally, I mean,
this comes this discussion and the
reason why it's become so inflamed is
because it comes in the middle of a very
very heated political context. In
America, we see an administration that
is, you know, using the abolition of DEI
as one of its, you know, articles of
faith. Isn't the danger of this example,
and that's why we all have to be really
careful, that this could get so badly
out of hand and some very innocent and
brilliant people could get thrown under
the bus unfairly?
>> There yes, there are dangers. I
don't believe we are facing a figure
akin to Donald Trump
being well, not head of state, but our
Prime Minister here.
>> Yes, but you can see the climate
changing, can't
>> Yes, I can, but I but I would look at
this from another angle. This was a time
of relatively low public confidence in
higher education, which is currently
going through financial crisis. There
are cuts and redundancies all over the
sector. I think it's really important
that the sector does everything it can
to regain public trust in what they do.
The sector is being decimated at the
moment and we have to show why we really
matter.
>> Go on, Professor Jones.
>> He's one person. He is one person and
the argument that you're making,
Professor Pace and many others in the
media, especially the right-wing
um um advocates of of getting rid of
uh Adi and people like him is that we
all all black academics need to be
looked at carefully in case they were
replica of Adi and that is what is going
to be happening from now on. You can't
deny that.
>> So, all academics
>> But shouldn't all academics be put
through a
>> No, shouldn't
>> Shouldn't you all be if if that's where
we're going, shouldn't every academic,
including you, uh Professor Pace, put
their work through a plagiarism
detector, everyone, regardless of color?
Is that where we're going?
>> I think that would be no bad thing and
often, certainly in my case, we do so. I
mean, I
I think I'd know if I'd plagiarized
stuff, uh but yes, I think work
generally should be done put through a
plagiarism detector and journals should
do that and recruitment panels should do
that.
>> Okay, we'll leave it there. Professor
Pace, Professor John, thank you very
much for your time, both of you.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay.